<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The way of life revealed and the way of death discovered wherein is declared man's happy estate before the fall, his miserable estate in the fall, and the way of restauration out of the fall into the image of God again ... : also the by-pathes, crooked wayes, wiles, snares, and temptations of the enemy of man's soul discover'd ... the utter end and final destruction of all false professions prophesied ... : also a call in the tender bowels of the love of God shed abroad in this day, age, and generation to all the scatterrd sheep upon the barren mountains of profession to return to the true shepherd Christ Jesus ... / Charles Marshall.</title>
            <author>Marshall, Charles, 1637-1698.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52034</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M746</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26188</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09382623</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09382623</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42915</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52034)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42915)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1312:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The way of life revealed and the way of death discovered wherein is declared man's happy estate before the fall, his miserable estate in the fall, and the way of restauration out of the fall into the image of God again ... : also the by-pathes, crooked wayes, wiles, snares, and temptations of the enemy of man's soul discover'd ... the utter end and final destruction of all false professions prophesied ... : also a call in the tender bowels of the love of God shed abroad in this day, age, and generation to all the scatterrd sheep upon the barren mountains of profession to return to the true shepherd Christ Jesus ... / Charles Marshall.</title>
                  <author>Marshall, Charles, 1637-1698.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>35 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42915:1"/>
            <p>THE WAY of LIFE REVEALED; AND THE VVAY of DEATH DISCOVERED.</p>
            <p>Wherein is declared, Man's Happy Eſtate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Fall, his Miſerable Eſtate in the Fall, and the Way of Reſtauration out of the Fall into the Image of God again, in which man was before the Fall.</p>
            <p>Alſo, the By-Pathes, Crooked Wayes, Wiles, Snares and Temptations of the Enemy of man's Soul diſcover'd, who has and doth go about as a Roaring Lyon, ſeeking how he may enſnare and devour thoſe who are in any meaſure eſcaping out of his Wayes of Death, and Deſtruction.</p>
            <p>The utter End and final Deſtruction of all falſe Profeſſions Propheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which have had their Riſe in the Night of Apoſtacy, through the Loſs of the Ancient Eternal Power of the Mighty God, by which the Gatherings to the Lord have been through Ages and Generations.</p>
            <p>Alſo a Call in the tender Bowels of the Love of God ſhed abroad in this Day, Age and Generation, to all the ſcattered Sheep upon the barren Mountains of Profeſſion, to return to the true Shepherd, Chriſt Jeſus, that ſo into the One Fold they may be gathered.</p>
            <p>Charles Marſhall.</p>
            <q>Go through, go through the Gates, prepare ye the Way of the People; caſt up, caſt up the High Way, gather out the Stones, lift up a Standard for the People. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Lord has proclaimed unto the End of the World, ſay ye to the Daughter of <hi>Sion, Behold thy Salvation cometh; behold his Reward is with him, and his Work before him,</hi>
               <bibl>Iſa. <hi>42.10, 11.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1674.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:42915:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:42915:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>BE ſerious when thou takeſt in hand to read this following Treatiſe, and have a ſingle Regard unto the inward Eſtate of thy Immortal Soul; and let thy Spirit bow down to the Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Spirit of God given thee to profit withal, that by it the Eye of thy Underſtanding may be opened, ſo wilt thou ſee the things herein contained, which concern thy own Eternal Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare: and let not thy own Thoughts and Imaginations in the Wiſdom from below (which is ſenſual and earthly) be Judge herein; but ſtand ſtill out of thy own Comprehendings, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendings and Deſcendings; and let a true and diligent Regard be had to the Word in thy Heart and Mouth, there placed, that thou mayſt obey it and do it; ſo will thy Heart be truly opened to read with Delight the Things herein, opened by the Spirit of Truth, which ſearches all things, yea, the deep things of God; and the Travel in Spirit (which is for the opening the Eyes of the Blind, and unſtopping of the Ears of the Deaf) will be anſwered, and the Lord God Almighty will have his Honour from his own Workmanſhip, and thou the Benefit; which is the Deſire, Travil and Breathings of him, who is a Traveller for <hi>Sion</hi>'s perfect Deliverance.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Briſtol <hi>
                     <date>the 7th of the 2d Moneth, in the Year 1673.</date>
                  </hi>
               </dateline>
               <signed>C. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:42915:3"/>
            <head>THE Way of Life REVEALED; AND THE WAY of DEATH DISCOVERED, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>IN the beginning God created the Heaven and the Earth; and after he had made all things on the Earth, he made Man in his own Image, formed him of the Duſt of the Ground, and breathed into him the Breath of Life, and Man became a Living Soul: and the Lord planted a Garden in <hi>Eden,</hi> and there he pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the man whom he had formed; and out of the Ground the Lord God made every Tree pleaſant to the Sight &amp; good for Food, to grow; the Tree of Life alſo in the midſt of the Garden, and the Tree of Knowledge of Good and Evil; And he that made man in this Eſtate gave him a Law to preſerve him therein, as the Scripture of Truth witneſſeth, ſaying, <hi>And the Lord God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the man, ſaying, Of every Tree in the Garden thou mayſt freely eat; but of the Tree of Knowledge of Good and Evil thou mayſt not eat; for, in the day thou eateſt thereof, thou ſhalt ſurely dye.</hi> Now God ſaw every thing that he had made, and behold it was very good; the Tree of Knowledge of Good and Evil was good, but not for Food: And man was indued with that Divine
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:42915:3"/>Wiſdom, that when the Lord God brought of every Beaſt of the Field and Fowl of the Air to <hi>Adam,</hi> he gave Names unto them; and whatſoever <hi>Adam</hi> called every living Creature, that was the Name thereof: So here was man's Station in the Image of God, a Living Soul, a Noble Plant, wholely a Right Seed, filled with Divine Wiſdom and Virtue, cloathed with Innocency, covered with Glory, adorned with celeſtial Beauty in the continual En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of the Love and Favour of the Eternal Being of all Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, having his daily Converſation with him that made him; no Death, no Darkneſs, no Sorrow, no Occaſion of Tears, no Tranſgreſſion, no Knowledge of Evil, dwelling in the Innocent Life it ſelf, placed in the Garden, into which came the River out of <hi>Eden</hi> that watered it. Oh bleſſed State! Oh happy Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on! Oh unexpreſſible Enjoyment, undeclarable Beauty and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry! 'Tis beyond the Tongue of Man to declare fully that bleſſed, happy Eſtate of Joy, Peace, Virtue, Purity, Holineſs, Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs and Fruition of Life, which man was in before he tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed the Royal Law of God, &amp;c.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Man's Miſerable Eſtate in the Fall.</head>
               <p>BUt now he, who kept not his firſt Habitation, neither abode in the Truth, envied man's Happineſs in the Truth, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (as a Serpent, more ſubtil then any Beaſt of the Field which the Lord God had made) came to the Woman (who out of the Man was made) and ſaid, <hi>Yea, hath God ſaid, Ye ſhall not eat of every Tree of the Garden?</hi> The Woman ſaid, <hi>We may eat of the Fruits of the Trees of the Garden, but of the Fruit of the Tree which is in the midſt of the Garden, God hath ſaid, Ye ſhall not eat, neither ſhall ye touch of it, leſt ye dye.</hi> And the Serpent ſaid to the Woman, <hi>Ye ſhall not ſurely dye; for God doth know, that in the day ye eat thereof then your Eyes ſhall be opened, and ye ſhall be as Gods, knowing Good and Evil:</hi> And here the Serpent got an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance. And when the Woman [mark] ſaw that the Tree was good for Food, and that it was pleaſant to the Eyes, and a Tree to be deſired to make one Wiſe, ſhe took of the Fruit, and did eat,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:42915:4"/>and gave alſo to her Husb and with her, and he did eat, and the Eyes [mark] of them both were opened: Here the God of the World prevailed, ſo as to open an Eye that ſaw Evil pleaſant, and to Blind the Eye in theſe Children of Diſobedience, that they ſhould no longer behold the Glory of God, &amp;c. And here they became na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, having loſt the Robe of Righteouſneſs and Garment of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, and then made Aprons of Fig leaves to cover their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs; and they heard the Voice of the Lord God walking in the Cool of the Day, and <hi>Adam</hi> and his Wiſe hid them elves from the Preſence of the Lord God; and the Lord God called unto <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Where art thou?</hi> And the Man ſaid, <hi>I heard thy Voice in the Garden, and I was afraid, becauſe I was Naked; and I hid my ſelf:</hi> And the Lord God ſaid, <hi>Who told thee that thou waſt naked? Haſt thou eaten of the Tree whereof I commanded thee that thou ſhouldſt not eat?</hi> Who began to excuſe himſelf, ſaying, <hi>The Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man thou gaveſt to be with me, ſhe gave me to eat, and I did eat:</hi> And the Lord God ſaid to the Woman, <hi>What is this that thou haſt done?</hi> And the Woman ſaid, <hi>The Serpent beguiled me, and I did eat:</hi> And the Lord God ſaid unto the Serpent, <hi>Becauſe thou haſt done this, curſed art thou above all Cattel, and above every Beaſt of the Field; on thy Belly ſhalt thougo, and Duſt ſhalt thou eat, &amp;c. And I will put Enmity between thee and the Woman, and between thy Seed and her Seed; it ſhall bruiſe thy Head, and thou ſhalt bruiſe his Heel.</hi> So the Lord ſent him forth from the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, to till the Ground, &amp;c. and placed at the Eaſt of the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of <hi>Eden</hi> Cherubims, and a Flaming Sword, which turned eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way to keep the Way of the Tree of Life.</p>
               <p>Oh miſerable Change! Oh deplorable Alteration! Oh lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table State, undeclarable undone Condition, unexpreſſible Fall! What! he that was in the Image of the Incorruptible Being, a Living Soul, inhabiting in the Garden of the Lord, where the Tree of Life was, and the Splendor of the Glory of the Divine Being was known and enjoyed; drove from all into the Earth, and not only ſo, but the Cherubims and Flaming Sword (that turneth eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way) placed to keep the Way of the Tree of Life! Be aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed oh Heavens at this, and be horribly afraid oh Earth! The Lord God brought up Children, and they Rebelled againſt him.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:42915:4"/>
               <p>Now what was the Cauſe and Ground, O ye Sons and Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Adam,</hi> that brought this horrible Change, that brought man into this deplorable State and Condition? Was it not Diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to the Righteous Law of God? Did not Sin enter into the World through Diſobedience, and Death by Sin? And is not Sin continued in the World through Diſobedience? Is there any other Way by which Sin enters now then it did then, and Death by Sin, which has reigned over all, and reigns over all who are in the fallen Eſtate from God, even over them that have not ſinned accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Similitude of <hi>Adam</hi>'s Tranſgreſſion? For all have not ſinned according to his Similitude, who was deceived with an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of an higher Eſtate then that in which the Lord God had placed him; But all Iniquity, of what Similitude ſoever, is one in the Ground, and becomes a Separator of man from his God: So the Ground of all Iniquity and Tranſgreſſion that ever was, is, or ſhall be, is man's Diſobeying the Righteous Law of God, Diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience whereunto bringeth Death.</p>
               <p>But what was that which in <hi>Adam</hi> dyed, and what was the Death; ſeeing that the Lord ſaid, <hi>In the Day thou eateſt of the Tree</hi> (before mentioned) <hi>thou ſhalt ſurely Dye;</hi> and yet, though he did eat thereof, he lived outwardly, and had Children?</p>
               <p>It was the Inward Man that dyed, which was ſo made by the Living Breath of the Almighty; for man going out of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of the Lord, by his Diſobedience came to be alienated from the Life of God, and ſo became inſenſible of that primary Life in which he was wholely a right Seed, and a noble Plant: In his Degeneration he became inwardly dead; the inward Senſes of the inward Man were loſt; the inward Ear was ſtopped; the inward Eye was blinded; the inward Sence of taſting how good the Lord is; the inward Feeling after the Divine Virtue (who is all Power, Life, Love and Joy) the inward Sence of Smelling his Garments (that ſmell of Myrrh, and of the Spikenard Spiritually) were all loſt; and inſtead thereof, an Ear opened that hearkened to the Voice of the Stranger, and an Eye opened that ſaw the forbidden Fruit pleaſant and deſirable, the Heavenly Cloathing of Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, Meakneſs and Reſignation loſt; and thus he came to be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God in the World: and here in this Eſtate Man was altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42915:5"/>out of a Capacity of abiding in the Garden, or partaking of the Heavenly Tree of Life, that was in the midſt thereof; and in this Eſtate are all the unconverted Sons and Daughters of men, notwithſtanding all Fig-leaf-Coverings of Profeſſions.</p>
               <p>But as the Law of the Spirit of Life breaketh forth in its Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation, and the Sons and Daughters of men come with it to be awakened, they will have the Sight and true Sence of their inward Eſtate and Condition, which will indeed cauſe a Cry to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe in the Soul, <hi>Oh wretched Eſtate! Oh miſerable Condition!</hi> And here the Entrance of Sin comes to be ſeen, which hath brought Death; for the Wages of Sin is Death, which was the Death that came over <hi>Adam,</hi> and over all ſince, that have diſobey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Righteous Spiritual Law of God, which is juſt, holy and good, and was before Tranſgreſſion, which Law bringeth to Chriſt, the Promiſed Seed, the Gift of God, which is Eternal Life.</p>
               <p>Now man being thus departed out of that Nature, Image and Seed in which man had his Being before Tranſgreſſion, is become the degenerate Plant of a ſtrange Vine before the Lord God that made him: And from the Sons and Daughters of men (as they ſtand joyned to this Nature and Seed of the Serpent, which hath defiled Man in Soul, Body and Spirit) proceed theſe Branches and Fruits of Iniquity, to wit, Pride; Envy; Emulation; Strife; Variance; Debate; Hatred; Wrath; Anger; Murder; Inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate Affection; Concupiſcence; Laſciviouſneſs; Wantonneſs; Vanity; Uncleanneſs; Fornication; Adulteries; Love to this World; Drunkenneſs; Revelling; Idleneſs; Swearing; Curſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; Cheating; Defrauding; Double-dealing; Evil-ſpeaking; Back-biting; Covetouſneſs; Idolatry; Witchcraft.</p>
               <p>Man being thus fallen from God into this miſerable, deplorable State, the infinite Being in his Endleſs, Boundleſs, Fathomleſs Loving-kindneſs hath opened a Way, by which Mankind might be reſtored up to himſelf again; which Way is the promiſed Seed, concerning whom he ſaid to the Serpent, <hi>I will put Enmity between thee and the Woman, and between thy Seed and her Seed; it ſhall bruiſe thy Head, and thou ſhalt bruiſe his Heel.</hi> So herein was the tender Mercy of the everlaſting God extended unto Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42915:5"/>in leaving a Seed; elſe all would have been as <hi>Sodom,</hi> and like unto <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> which God deſtroyed with Fire in his Wrath: So this is that one Seed on which he hath laid Help, who is migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to ſave, who is the Image of the Inviſible God, the Firſt-born of every Creature (in which Image Man was before the Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion) who was glorified with the Father before the World began; This is He of whom in the Name of the great <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah</hi> I give Teſtimony, That He is the Way of Life and Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and that there is no other Name by which any man can be ſaved, then by him who was, and is, and is to come; who was from Everlaſting to Everlaſting, the Rock of Ages, which followed <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and was in the Church in the Wilderneſs, as <hi>Stephen</hi> teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied before he was ſtoned to Death: This is He who is without Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of Days or End of Life; who in the Fulneſs of Time was manifeſt, taking on him not the Nature of Angels, but the Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> for whom there was a Body prepar'd to do the Will of his Father; who, after he had accompliſh'd it, aſcended where he was before, far above all Heavens, that he might fill all: This is the <hi>Emanuel, God with us; Jeſus, the Saviour; Chriſt, the Anointed,</hi> who hath been called by ſeveral Names, &amp; ſpoken of under ſeveral De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominations and Appellations, through the Mouthes of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants the Prophets and Apoſtles in Ages and Generations by paſt; This is the only Beloved of the Ranſomed, and this is our Friend.</p>
               <p>And now he is ariſen and ariſing (who is the Ancient of Dayes) in the Might of his Power, and is revealing himſelf, the <hi>Good Old Way</hi> and <hi>Path of Life,</hi> whoſe Out-goings have been from Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting; in which Way <hi>Abel, Seth, Enoch, Noah, Abraham, Iſaac, Jacob,</hi> and all the <hi>Servants, Prophets, Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Saints of the Moſt High God</hi> walked through all Ages and Generations; which Way was before all the invented Ways and Worſhips were, which have been ſet up in the Will and Time of Man; for all the holy Men of God and Saints of the Moſt High worſhipped God in the Spirit of Holineſs, in which they were accepted of him, who is the God of the Spirits of all Fleſh; And no outward Performance whatever, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by any through Ages and Generations, was any farther ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable unto the Lord, but as performed in this Spirit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:42915:6"/>
               <head>The Way of Reſtoration out of the Fall, into the Image of God again, in which Man was before the Fall, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>BUt how Salvation comes to be wrought by him, and how Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind may be brought again into him, who is the Way, the Truth and the Life, and brought from under the Power and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of the Seed of the Serpent (in which by Nature all have been the Children of Wrath) is indeed the thing that lieth on my Spirit weightily to demonſtrate, having obtained Mercy to ſee this Way of Life and Salvation revealed and opened; and not only ſo, but a Neceſſity hath been and is upon me to preach the Goſpel of Chriſt Jeſus, and declare the Way of Life and Salvation to my Country-men through this Iſland of <hi>England;</hi> and now a Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is alſo upon my Spirit, to leave a Teſtimony of the ſame on Record.</p>
               <p>This is generally confeſſed, that in the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> all dyed, and in the ſecond Man <hi>Adam</hi> (Chriſt the Lord) all come to be made alive again: But how Mankind comes out of this State of Death in the firſt Man <hi>Adam,</hi> into this State of Life, in the ſecond Man <hi>Adam,</hi> is that which the Wiſdom of this World never knew, never ſaw, never underſtood, nor comprehended truly or rightly; Man by that Wiſdom hath only imagined &amp; conceived ſomething in the Carnal Mind concerning this great Myſtery, and therein hath ſet up many Inventions of the Way of Life and Salvation; And into theſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Wayes of man's Inventions and Imaginations (ſet up in the fallen Wiſdom of Man) there have been the ſeveral Calls, <hi>Lo here, Lo there;</hi> but the Day is dawned and appearing, and now break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth more and more (magnified and praiſed be the Name of the Infinite, Almighty God) wherein all invented Wayes, ſet
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:42915:6"/>up in the Will and Wiſdom of Man, that is Earthly, Senſual and Deviliſh, ſhall come to an End.</p>
               <p>And now, in the Name of the Mighty God, all the graven I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, the Work of Men's Hands, and Earthly Wiſdoms ſhall be broken to pieces and ground to Powder; the Mouth of the Lord of Hoſts hath ſpoken it, who will perform it by the Might of his Arm, and by the Strength of his Power.</p>
               <p>And therefore Tremble, Tremble, all ye Image-makers of all ſorts, who have been making and framing Likeneſſes of the Way of Life and Salvation in your fallen Wiſdoms and corrupt Wills, and have mad Gods thereof, and have fallen, bowed down to, and worſhipped them; ſo that it may be ſaid of <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> (ſo called) as it was once ſaid of <hi>Iſrael, As are thy Cities, ſo are thy Gods, O</hi> Iſrael!</p>
               <p>But now is the Fulneſs of Time come and coming, wherein the ancient Way of Holineſs (in which the Righteous walked through all Ages and Generations) is caſt up, manifeſt and manifeſting; which Way is Chriſt Jeſus (the Gift of the Father's Love unto the Sons and Daughters of men) who hath, as before-mentioned, been preached up and declared of by his Servants, Meſſengers, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles under ſeveral Denominations and Appellati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, according as he was pleaſed to manifeſt himſelf in &amp; to them, and as his Spirit gave them Utterance: Amongſt many other Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellations he hath been declared a <hi>Prieſt</hi> forever, after the Order of <hi>Melchizedeck;</hi> the <hi>Rock</hi> that followed <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who was in the Church in the Wilderneſs; a King; a Law-giver; VVonderful Councellor; Prince of Peace; a Branch; a Light, to lighten the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> the Arm of God's Salvation; a Covenant; Meſſiah; a Leader; a Commander; a Captain; the Horn of God's A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed; a Stone of Stumbling; a Foundation laid in <hi>Ston;</hi> the Corner-ſtone; the VVord of God; the VVord that was in the Beginnning; the True Light, that lighteth every man that cometh into the VVorld; the Truth; the VVay and the Life; King of Kings; Lord of Lords; Chriſt; <hi>Emanuel;</hi> Jeſus; the Beginning of the Creation of God: the Firſt-born of every Creature; the Firſt-begotten from the Dead; the Faithful VVitneſs; Alpha and Omega; Bright and Morning Star; the Image of the Inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble God; the Off-ſpring of <hi>David:</hi> Under theſe, I ſay, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:42915:7"/>Names and Denominations hath he been ſpoken and declared of and by, who ſtill hath a Name that no man knoweth but himſelf, who is that One Eternal Fountain of Bleſſedneſs, and the One Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Saviour; and there is no other beſides him, although diverſly denominated, according as his Spirit gave Utterance to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate him to thoſe unto whom his Servants ſpake, propheſied and wrote.</p>
               <p>And now by the Ancient Power of the Holy Everlaſting God, is he preached up under the Denomination of LIGHT, in this Iſland of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> according as was propheſied of old, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> chap. 49. verſ. 6. who ſaid, <hi>Is it a light thing that thou ſhouldſt be my Servant, to raiſe up the Tribes of</hi> Jacob, <hi>and to preſerve the Reſtored of</hi> Iſrael? <hi>I will alſo give thee for a</hi> Light <hi>to the</hi> Gentiles, <hi>that thou mayſt be my Salvation unto the Ends of the Earth;</hi> which is one with the Teſtimony of <hi>John,</hi> chap. 1. ſaying, <hi>In the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God; the ſame was in the Beginning with God; all things were made by him, and without him was not any thing made that was made; In him was Life, and the Life</hi> [mark] <hi>was the</hi> Light <hi>of men; and the Light ſhineth in the Darkneſs, and the Darkneſs compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth it not. There was a Man ſent from God, whoſe Name was</hi> John; <hi>the ſame came for a Witneſs, to bear Witneſs of the Light, that all through him might believe: He was not that Light, but was ſent to bear Witneſs of that</hi> Light, <hi>that was the true Light, which lightneth every man that comes into the World, &amp;c.</hi> And to this agrees the Teſtimony of Juſt <hi>Simeon,</hi> who came by the Spirit into the Temple, and took the Child Jeſus into his Arms, and ſaid, <hi>Lord, now letteſt thou thy Servant depart in Peace, according to thy Word; for my Eyes have ſeen thy Salvation, which thou haſt prepared before the Face of all People, a</hi> Light <hi>to lighten the</hi> Gentiles, <hi>and the Glory of thy People</hi> Iſrael. This is He of whom we Teſtifie, whoſe <hi>Light</hi> is the VVay to Life: <hi>And this is the Condemnation, that</hi> Light <hi>is come into the World, and men love Darkneſs rather then Light, becauſe their Deeds are Evil; For every one</hi> [mark] <hi>that doth Evil hateth the Light, neither cometh to the Light, leſt his Deeds ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved; but he that doth Truth cometh to the Light, that his Deeds may be made manifeſt that they are wrought in God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now this <hi>Light,</hi> which the Servants of the Moſt High teſtified
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:42915:7"/>of, is that which hath been ſpoken of and denominated under ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Names; For this Manifeſtation of God in man is ſometimes called the Word, the Spirit, the Law, the Grace of God; now the VVord, Light, Grace, Law, Spirit, are all one in Nature, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though diverſly named: <hi>Moſes</hi> called it the <hi>Word,</hi> and directed to this Word in the Heart and in the Mouth, which <hi>Paul</hi> (that il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminated Man) rehearſing, ſaith, <hi>Say not in thy Heart</hi> [mark] <hi>Who ſhall aſcend into Heaven (that is, to bring Chriſt down from above) or who ſhall deſcend into the Deep (that is, to bring Chriſt up again from the Dead) But what ſaith it? The</hi> Word <hi>is nigh thee, even in thy Mouth, and in thy Heart; that is the Word of Faith that we preach.</hi> This is the ſure Word of Prophecy unto which <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> directs to take heed, as unto a <hi>Light</hi> that ſhineth in a dark place, until the Day dawn, and the Day-ſtar ariſe in the Heart, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Light</hi> is the Law of the Spirit of Life, where-with <hi>Paul</hi> was acquainted, that warred in his Mind againſt the Law of Sin and Death (which was in his Members) This <hi>Light</hi> is the Law in the Heart, and the Spirit in the inward parts, the New Covenant of God Almighty; This is that which converts the Soul; which <hi>Law Paul</hi> delighted in according to the inward Man; This <hi>Law</hi> is <hi>Light,</hi> of which the Scriptures of Truth plentifully teſtifie; This is that <hi>Grace</hi> that <hi>Paul</hi> declared, brings Salvation, which hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to all men; which <hi>Law, Light, Spirit, Grace, Gift</hi> hath in meaſures, as <hi>God's Talents,</hi> appeared unto all men, which tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth all that are lead, taught and guided by it, to deny all <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and Worldly Luſts;</hi> and not only ſo, but alſo, <hi>to live Soberly, Godly and Righteouſly in this preſent Evil World:</hi> This is that <hi>Grace</hi> which the Lord (the Giver thereof) ſaid to <hi>Paul, was ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for him</hi> to deliver him from the Temptation (the Thorn in the Fleſh) of which the ſame Apoſtle ſaid unto the <hi>Epheſians, By Grace ye are ſaved, &amp;c.</hi> And this is the Manifeſtation of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit (ſpoken of by <hi>Paul</hi>) which is given to every man to profit withal: And this is that good Spirit of the Lord given to <hi>Iſrael, who rebelled againſt it,</hi> as the old World did, unto whom the Lord ſaid, <hi>My Spirit ſhall not alwayes ſtrive with Man;</hi> of which <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ord, Law, Light, Grace</hi> and <hi>Spirit,</hi> given to be the Leader and Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Mankind out of Sin, Death and Darkneſs (into which
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:42915:8"/>Man fell through diſobeying the Righteous Law of God, as is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore declared) the holy Scriptures give clear and full Teſtimony, as hath been demonſtrated. But now, that which is ready to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe, is an Objection in ſome (whoſe Underſtandings are not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, whoſe ſearchings to comprehend, and Inquiries after the Way of man's Salvation ſtand in that Wiſdom that is from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and in the Will and Reaſon of Man degenerated from the Life of God) which is, VVhether the preaching up this <hi>Word, Light, Law, Spirit</hi> and <hi>Grace of God</hi> manifeſt within, hath not a Tendency to make Chriſt Jeſus his Appearance in the Fleſh, his Sufferings, Death, Reſurrection and Aſcenſion to be Invalid? Unto which I anſwer, Nay; Foraſmuch as no Perſons ever did, do, or ſhall truly ſee, diſcern, know, underſtand or enjoy the Benefit of Chriſt Jeſus his Manifeſtation in the Fleſh, but as their Hearts were, are or ſhall be opened, and Underſtanding illuminated by the Light, which is a Meaſure of the Divine Fulneſs that dwelt in him, and is communicated to, and placed in all Immortal Souls, as the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Love of God, extended in the Son of his Love to all the Families of the Earth, as the Revealer and Diſcoverer of the VVill of him from whoſe Divine Fulneſs it comes, and iſſueth forth it ſelf univerſally; for the Scripture thus witneſſeth, that <hi>No man knoweth the things of a man, ſave the spirit of a man which is in him; even ſo the things of God knows no man but the Spirit of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Hearts of the <hi>Jews</hi> not being ſeaſoned with this <hi>Grace of God,</hi> and ignorant of the <hi>Gift of God,</hi> which is <hi>Eternal Life,</hi> they neither diſcerned, loved, nor received Chriſt Jeſus when manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in that outward bodily Appearance, but rejected him, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they profeſſed Love, Honour and Regard to the Prophets, and were in Expectation of the Fulfilling their Prophecies of the Coming of the Meſſiah, who in due time came, and yet they did not receive him, but inſtead thereof ſet themſelves againſt him, taking Counſel from time to time how they might ſlay him, though in Words they profeſt an earneſt waiting for him: So in this Day, Age and Generation there are many, who by their words do profeſs they believe his Coming in the Fleſh, and his Sufferings, Death, Reſurrection and Aſcenſion; but yet having their Faith conſiſting in outward Notions, and having no inward Experience of the End of his Coming, nor of the Virtue of his Sufferings,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:42915:8"/>Death, Reſurrection, &amp;c. they are Enemies in their Minds to his ſecond Appearance, and coming without Sin unto Salvation: So there is a Neceſſity for all the Sons and Daughters of men to come to, and obey this Divine Spiritual Principle, which is placed in their Conſciences by the Living, Eternal God, that thereby the Eye which hath been blinded through Diſobedience (by the God of the VVorld) may be opened; for until this in ſome meaſure be effected, the Myſtery of Godlineſs (which is great) can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be ſeen nor underſtood; and therefore Chriſt ſaid, finding the Woman of <hi>Samaria</hi> ignorant of himſelf (who was and is that great Myſtery, and the Gift of the Father's Love) <hi>If thou knoweſt the Gift of God, and who it is that ſaith unto thee, Give me to drink, thou wouldſt have asked of him, and he would have given thee Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Water.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Travail in Spirit of the Meſſengers and Servants of the Moſt High in Ages paſt, was the ſame as now is, viz. <hi>To turn People from Darkneſs unto Light, and from the Power of Satan to the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Living God;</hi> thereby in no wiſe invalidating Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus his Manifeſtation in that Bodily Appearance, neither his Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, Death, Reſurrection or Aſcenſion; but brings all People guided thereby, unto that which will open the Eyes of their Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings, whereby they all come unto ſuch a Condition and ſpiritual Underſtanding, as to ſee and know their Benefit by that Appearance of the Saviour of the World; for this we teſtifie, <hi>All are perfected by that one Offering that are ſanctified.</hi> But here ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth another Objection by ſome, who may come ſo far as to own and confeſs, <hi>That there is a Principle or Light in man, that diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereth Sin, and teacheth man to do Juſtly and Equally</hi> (which ſome call <hi>Morality</hi>) but, <hi>That this Light or Principle in man is of a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Property, and of the Nature and Quality of the Divine Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> many for want of Underſtanding do deny, and ſo are found Oppoſers of Truth it ſelf, and ſtumble at the Corner-ſtone, which indeed in all Generations hath been to many men a <hi>Stone of Stumbling</hi> &amp; <hi>Rock of Offence,</hi> which Thouſands (giving themſelves up to be guided by their own Wiſdoms and Prudence) reject, yea, thoſe accounted the <hi>Wiſe Maſter-Builders, Profeſſors of God and Chriſt,</hi> being ignorant of the Root and Off-ſpring of <hi>David,</hi> have and yet do reject this <hi>Corn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>-Stone.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:42915:9"/>
               <p>Now, for the ſake of all who do or may deſire after the true and ſaving Knowledge of Chriſt Jeſus, it is on my Spirit yet further to open and manifeſt the Original, Nature a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Property of this Principle and Light, whoſe Original and Foun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>n is the Eternal Being and Everlaſting Ocean of Divine Fulneſs, and its Nature and Quality is one with this Fountain from which it comes: <hi>John</hi> teſtified, <hi>In the Beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, &amp;c. In him was Life, and the Life was the Light of men:</hi> He alſo teſtify'd, <hi>That he was not that Light, but came for a Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to bear witneſs, that that was the True Light, which lighteth every Man that cometh into the World:</hi> So the Original of this <hi>Light</hi> is Chriſt Jeſus, the <hi>Word.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſome may query thus, <hi>Is Chriſt the Light in every man?</hi> To which I anſwer; Chriſt doth appear by his Light in every man; and the Light (which cometh from Chriſt) is in every man; as is clearly demonſtrated from the Scriptures of Truth: And, though I account it unneceſſary to anſwer the curious Inquiries of ſuch, who ſeeking to know much, <hi>do not walk anſwerable to what they know;</hi> yet for the ſake of ſuch, whoſe Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings are not open'd, and yet are inquiring the Way to <hi>Sion,</hi> I add this Similitude: <hi>The Natural Sun is placed by the Creator to lighten the Outward World, and doth extend from its Body a Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of its Light and Natural Property, ſhining on the Juſt and the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt, and ſo doth daily give forth of that Vertue which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent in its ſelf: when the Sun ſhineth on an Object whatſoever, we ſometimes ſay, the Sun there appears; and other times we ſay, there is the Sun; the Propriety of either of which manner of Expreſſions I ſuppoſe none will queſtion; for Light in that Appearance is ſeen, and Vertue is felt penetrating to the Refreſhment of our Natural Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; and this Light and Heat is inſeparable from the Fulneſs; and notwithſtanding it daily ſhineth and diſplayeth its Vertuous Life into and over all the Earth and its Inhabitants, yet its Body is not any way exhauſted or altered through Ages and Generations.</hi> And ſo I ſay, that Chriſt, the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Fountain of Life,</hi> the <hi>Sun of Righteouſneſs,</hi> the <hi>Ocean and Fulneſs of Spiritual Light, Life and Vertue</hi> (from whence is communicated a Meaſure of his Nature, Property and Quality) is given of the Father to enlighten all the Sons and Daughters of men, who accordingly are all enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:42915:9"/>with his Spiritual Appearance; and though this Appearance cannot be call'd the Fulneſs, yet being a Meaſure of that Fulneſs, it is one in Nature &amp; Property with, and inſeparable from the Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: And though through its Virtue Life is daily communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated unto the Sons of men (who waiting for the Appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance thereof, as for the Morning-Light, cannot live unto God without it) yet doth he admit of no Diminution, Alteration or Change; but all Fulneſs of Divine Light, Life and Glory doth and ſhall through every Age and Generation remain with him: And albeit the Vail of Darkneſs hath over-ſhadowed the Hearts of ſome, ſo as when we give Teſtimony unto the Univerſal Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of the Sun of Rightcouſneſs in the Hearts of all the Sons and Daughters of men, they are ready to ſay, <hi>Such a Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony leads to the Diminiſhing of that Glory and Honour which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs unto him as he is the Fulneſs, and ſitting at the Right Hand of the Father;</hi> inferring from ſuch our Teſtimony, as if, whilſt <hi>we teſtifie to his Appearance in our Hearts, we exclude his Preſence to be elſe-where:</hi> which Inference, I ſay, is as irrational as it would be for any to conclude, That <hi>becauſe we ſay of the ſhining and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of the Sun, there is the Sun, or the Sun there appears; therefore we exclude the Being of the Sun elſe-where:</hi> For its Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue is communicated to our Natural Bodies, every one having in meaſure ſome Enjoyment of the Virtue or Light of the Natural Sun, which is Light to the Eye, even as the Outward Eye is Light to or of the Natural Body; and whoſoever they are, whoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible Senſes are quickened by the influencing Virtue, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from the Eternal Sun of Righteouſneſs, do thereby ſee and diſcern that theſe things are according to the clear Manifeſtation of Truth in their inward parts, and from a true Sence thereof can of a Truth give this certain Teſtimony, <hi>That Chriſt, the Lord, by his holy quickening Spirit hath appeared in them, to the quickening of their immortal Souls;</hi> and that through believing in the Light, and Obedience to his Appearance, being come out of that State which is reprobated by the Lord, can of certain experimental Knowledge ſay, <hi>Chriſt is in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Hope of Glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo when we direct People to this <hi>Word, Light, Law, Grace</hi> and <hi>Spirit,</hi> we do not thereby intend, that Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>the Light
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:42915:10"/>of the World</hi> and <hi>Gift of God,</hi> is not the true Saviour, Redeemer and Reconciler of Mankind unto God.</p>
               <p>Now this <hi>Word, Light, Law, Grace</hi> and <hi>Spirit</hi> (which is one in Nature) doth lead and guide the Souls and Spirits of all ſuch as obey it, up to God, the Fountain, from whom it comes; and no man comes to ſee its Nature and Original but ſuch who are led by it; for in the Light of the Lord alone man cometh to ſee Light, &amp; to have an Underſtanding of the Original from whence it ſprings: before this be ſeen or underſtood the Mind of man muſt be brought down out of all its own Willings and Runnings, Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendings &amp; Searchings into the Principle of Light, therein to ſee a Death to his own Will, and be comprehended into this Light; and ſo man comes to have an Underſtanding to know him that is true, and to be in him that is true.</p>
               <p>Now as any are convinced of and converted by this Heavenly Principle (which is placed in the Conſcience, there given to be a Guide and Leader unto Mankind) they are led thereby out of Darkneſs, wherein they have been, while yet the Light ſhone in Darkneſs, in which Darkneſs no man ever comprehended this Light or Heavenly Grace, which ſometimes moves through the Darkneſs on the Depth of man's Underſtanding, reproving and diſcovering Darkneſs, cauſing man to hear its ſmall ſtill Voice, moving in man God-wards, &amp; ſo daily continues without Change, reproving man whilſt he remains in <hi>Rebellion</hi> and <hi>Diſobedience</hi> all the time of his <hi>Viſitation,</hi> and approving and giving Peace un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to man when he is <hi>Obedient.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Principle of Light remains intire in its own Purity; and although man may change, and alter, and go from it, and rebel againſt it, and thereby become one of them of whom <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>that rebel againſt the Light, and thereby knows not the Way of it; but gives way to the Working of the God of the World, to be drawn out into the fading periſhing things:</hi> yet this Principle remains im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable in it ſelf, being of and from the Immutable Unchangeable Being, and remains with man until it be taken from him, and he be caſt into utter Darkneſs.</p>
               <p>The firſt Operation of this heavenly Light amongſt thoſe who are convinced by and turned to it, the Gift of the Father (which Chriſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:42915:10"/>Jeſus in his Parable to the <hi>Jews</hi> compared to a Grain of <hi>Muſtard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeed,</hi> and to a <hi>little Leaven, which a Woman took &amp; hid in three Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of Meal until the whole came to be leavened</hi>) is, to ſhew man his in ward State and Condition; and the firſt Step in the Way of Life is, to be turned to this holy Principle, that teacheth the Obedient to know God ſavingly; and when by this Principle man comes to have a true Sight and Sence of his fallen Eſtate, and ſees how he hath tranſgreſſed againſt that Eternal Being that gave him Life and Breath (who notwithſtanding in his <hi>Long-Suffering waiteth long to be Gracious, and knocketh at the Door of the Heart, and hath ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by his Divine Light</hi>) the true Sight and Sence hereof will break the Heart, and tender the Spirit before the Lord; and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the weighty Sence of the great Burden of Sin and Iniquity, there will be a crying out, <hi>My Sins they are too heavy for me to bean, and mine Iniquities are gone over my Head, as Paul</hi> did, ſaying, <hi>Oh Wretched Man that I am! who ſhall deliver me from the Body of this Death?</hi> And here comes the Eye to be opened that ſeeth him, whom man in his Diſobedience hath pierced afreſh, and put to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen Shame: and then there will be Dayes of Mourning and Wail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing becauſe of him, and this is truly the Day of <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Trouble: And in the Sence of this Deplorable Fallen Eſtate, and the Long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuffering of the Lord, and the Long-ſtriving of his Spirit, thou wilt ſee, that in the Juſtice of God Eternal <hi>Death might be thy Portion;</hi> but that which brings into this Sence, begets a ſecret Cry in the Immortal Soul after a <hi>Deliverer</hi> and <hi>Saviour,</hi> and will alſo give a true Sence and Sight, <hi>that there is no way for thy Soul to be ranſomed, but in and through the tender Mercy of the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt;</hi> which thou wilt ſee can no other way be effectually be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun in thee, but in the Way of the Judgments of the Lord; <hi>For 'tis through Judgment that</hi> Zion <hi>is redeemed, and her Converts with Righteouſneſs:</hi> And here alſo thou wilt ſee that the Meaſure of the Sufferings of Chriſt yet behind muſt be filled up in thee; <hi>for no other Way can any man paſs unto Life, Peace and Joy with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Spirits, but the Way the Captain of Salvation paſſed, which was through Death;</hi> and here thou wilt begin to arm thy ſelf with the ſame Mind: For none ceaſeth any farther from Sin, but as they ſuffer in the Fleſh the cruciſying of the Affections and Luſts thereof; and here the End of the Goſpel's Preaching comes to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:42915:11"/>be known and witneſſed, which was and is, <hi>that all man might be judged as men in the Fleſh, that ſo they might live according to God in the Spirit;</hi> and in this ſpiritual inward Sence &amp; Exerciſe the Lord God Almighty will bow down his Ear, &amp; Anſwer the Cryes of thy Awakened Soul, and manifeſt his Word of Power, which all in this State and Paſſage will know to be ſharper then any <hi>Two-edged Sword,</hi> piercing to the dividing aſunder of thy Immortal Soul from the Spirit and Nature of Tranſgreſſion, and its Working daily (as Subjection and Obedience is yielded unto it) dividing and making a Separation between Joynts and Marrow, giving thee daily a Diſcerning of the Thoughts and Intents of thy Heart.</p>
               <p>And as the Soul, Mind and Heart gives up in Love to God, freely to follow him in the Way of his Judgments, and gives up to the Sword of the Lord that which is for the Sword, and that which is for Deſtruction to be deſtroyed; thus will the pretious Work of the Lord proſper. And although this be a Time of <hi>Sorrow,</hi> and a Time of <hi>Trouble, Travail</hi> and <hi>Anguiſh;</hi> yet notwithſtanding it is a Good Day: therefore ſtrive not to get from under it, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to make haſte; <hi>for the true godly Sorrow worketh the true Repentance, which is never to be repented of;</hi> and after the true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance follows the true Knowledge of Remiſſion &amp; Forgiveneſs; and ſo thy Inquities by the Judgments of the Lord God Almighty come to be blotted out; and then <hi>the Times of Refreſhment come from the Preſence of the Lord, and from the Glory of his Power, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as there is a faithful abiding in, inward Watchfulneſs, and continual Obedience to this Heavenly Light, in which the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Work of God was known, there will be a going on from Step to Step in the Foot ſteps of the Flock of Chriſt Jeſus, and a growing from Strength to Strength (over Sin and the Nature thereof) and from one Degree of Grace to another; and as there is a faithful Perſeverance in this Divine Principle, the Eye of the Underſtanding will be ſingle, and here every thing which hath or doth let will be ſeen, and the Soul never ſtart aſide from an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Travil, until that which hindereth be taken out of the Way, and until thou ſeeſt all the Rule and Authority of the Enemy to be ſubdued under the Feet of the Lord's Anointed, and the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Soul upon his Shoulders, whoſe Right it is to Raign over all.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:42915:11"/>
               <p>And here Salvation, Redemption and Reſtoration is effectually injoyed, through the Effectual Working and Operating of the Almighty Power and Arm of God Almighty, unto whom be the Glory of his own Work forever; and ſo here will be a growing and increaſing, until there is a coming into that pretious State and Image in which man was before he fell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The By Pathes, Crooked Wayes, Wiles and Snares of the Enemy Diſcovered.</head>
               <p>NOw when the Mind is turned to this <hi>Divine Heavenly Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple,</hi> and that therein the Work of the Lord is begun (which before is ſaid, <hi>is the bringing man into a Real Senſible Knowledge of his State and Condition</hi>) then will the ſame <hi>Deſtroyer</hi> that brought man into Bondage at firſt, and hath kept him in Bondage, begin to work cunningly, and every way endeavour <hi>to deſtroy the Work of God begun in the Soul;</hi> and that he may accompliſh his End, he will go about every way, ſeeking an Entrance, <hi>and will lay his Temptations ſuitable to the Propenſity or Inclinations of the Creature.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the Heart and Mind be <hi>bowed down</hi> under the <hi>weighty Sence of Iniquity,</hi> the <hi>Sins</hi> committed coming in order, and the <hi>many Tranſgreſſions</hi> in ſight, through which the <hi>Sorrow</hi> and <hi>Bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs</hi> is great, here the Enemy will work in his <hi>Transformings,</hi> and although <hi>in Appearance like the Light,</hi> yet <hi>in Nature contrary thereto:</hi> For, albeit the <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Appearance of God</hi> gives the certain <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> of the <hi>inward State,</hi> and brings <hi>Sorrow be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of Sir,</hi> and ſhews the <hi>Mountain of Iniquity,</hi> and the <hi>exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Hills of Tranſgreſſion,</hi> yet its Workings inwardly beget a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Hope of <hi>Overcoming by the Lord's Strength;</hi> but then the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy,</hi> when he ſeeth the Soul <hi>bewed down,</hi> as aforeſaid, oftentimes <hi>afflicteth,</hi> and <hi>brings down the Mind into <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief of ever Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming,</hi> thereby endeavouring <hi>to ſink the Soul down into Deſpair,</hi> knowing, if he overcomes he ſtill keeps under his Power, although
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:42915:12"/>in another Appearance; but all that are exerciſed on this kind, waiting on the Lord ſingly, with the Mind ſtayed in the Light, this Snare will be diſcovered; for, as I ſaid, <hi>although the true Appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of God's Heavenly Light and Grace brings a Day of Trouble, Sorrow and Anguiſh, yet that Sorrow it not a Sorrow without Hope;</hi> but the Enemy's Working is, to bring into a <hi>Sorrow, Trouble</hi> and <hi>Anguiſh</hi> without Hope, and to draw down the Spirit into the <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Darkneſs,</hi> where there is no order,</p>
               <p>But now, when the Enemy of the Soul's Peace is diſcovered in this his Working, and the Heart and Soul through the Love and Power of God is comforted, incouraged and refreſhed, and rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed up into a Meaſure of the Living Hope, Satisfaction and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent; then the old, crooked, ſubtil Serpent endeavours to lead from off the inward daily Travail, that ſo Judgment may not be brought forth into Victory; and ſo draw up the Mind into a Falſe Perſwaſion of Obedience and Diligeuce, whenas there is not an Abiding in that which gives a true Sight and Sence of the State and Condition: And as before he would have deſtroyed the Hope that is an Anchor ſure and ſtedfaſt, ſo now on the other hand, he would beget a Faſle Hope and Confidence, and ſo bring out of the Daily Croſs, through which the Nature which hath alienated from God ſhould be deſtroyed.</p>
               <p>And if the Workings of the Enemy be ſeen and overcome in both theſe Wiles and Snares, on the Right Hand and on the Leſt, and that the Work proſpereth even until much be ſubjected, and that (through the daily Obedience to the Heavenly Power) much is ſlain, and that the Heart and Mind comes in a good meaſure to be cleanſed, and that in pure Obedience and conſtant Faithfulneſs in this Light of Righteouſneſs, a good Progreſs is made through the Adminiſtration of Condemnation (that is Glorious in its time) and that ſomething of pure Peace and heavenly Joy ſprings and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes in the Heart and Soul; here again the Enemy will be ſubtilly at work, to betray and lead aſide, in perſwading to ſit down now, as if all were done; and ſo lead out from the feeding on the Tree of Life, to feed on the Tree of Knowledge of Good and Evil: and ſo lead out into a Liberty to break the Commandment of the Lord; and here at firſt ſubtilly and cunningly draws the Mind out ſo far as to take a little Liberty, and draws the Mind ſomewhat
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:42915:12"/>from that diligent Watchfulneſs, Dread, Fear and Awe it was in before in the inward Travail of Spirit: And here if the deſtroying ſubtil Enemy can but prevail a little, he will lead out of the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Harmleis Life, and ſo gradually lead a little forth, and ſo by degrees openeth an Eye that may ſee ſomething in the outward vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible things that may ſomewhat affect the Mind; and as here he prevails, and cauſeth his Work to proſper (which he doth ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, gradually and hiddenly) the Eye that was opened comes again, through Diſobedience, to be in ſome meature blinded; and here Loſs is ſuſtained, even before the Unwatchful is aware. And ſo the Working of the Enemy firſt is, <hi>to cauſe ſuch to make Shipwrack of Faith in a little meaſure;</hi> that is, not to have the daily Belief to ſtand in the Power, the daily Injoyment of which coming to be left by degrees, there will then be a Turning from the Power of Godlineſs, into the Form thereof: And although at ſometimes the Eternal Power of the Lord God may be felt in this Eſtate, yet there being not a daily feeling after it, the Injoyment thereof (as to true Refreſhment &amp; Conſolation) comes to be loſt, &amp; an Image comes up in its place; and the Enemy provides and preſents ſome Object or Objects, ſo to take up the Mind, as that by degrees he may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in, and defile the Mind, and draw it out from its true Guide, ſo as alſo to make Shipwrack of a good Conſcience.</p>
               <p>And now, if the Enemy be diſcovered in theſe his Workings (before he can ſo effect his Work, as to bring Death and Darkneſs over again) and that the Power of the Lord breaks his Snares, and gives a true weighty Sence thereof (through which Trouble and Anguiſh of Spirit comes) here he will again transform and begin to work, as in the beginning of the Work, like the Condemning Power of the Lord, endeavouring to lead the Mind down into De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair of ever recovering again into the Former Condition, and hereby endeavour to draw the Mind to look at him that hath ſtung, that ſo the Remedy (the <hi>Soul-Ranſoming Power of the Lord</hi>) may not be felt after, nor looked at; but here (as there is a true Regard to the Lord, and a waiting upon him in the Way of his Judgments, having the Faith and Confidence to ſtand in his Power) the Backſliding will be hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed; and returning and diligently keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Light, the Power of the Lord God Almighty will work over that which hath Hurt, and endeavoured like a Rearing Lyon to deſtroy, &amp;c. and ſo leads on the Way again.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:42915:13"/>
               <p>But when Deliverance is known again from this deadly Snare, and the Work again goes on proſperouſly until the Houſe be ſwept and garniſhed, and there is a Paſſage known and witneſſed from Death unto Life, and the Adminiſtration of Condemnation being paſſed through, and the Spirit that ruled in the diſobedient Eſtate caſt out, and the Openings of that which doth exceed in Glory (the Adminiſtration of the Spirit) being known, here the Enemy will again Transform, and with all his Power and Strength in the Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation (as an <hi>Angel of Light</hi>) work by his Temptation on the Right Hand and on the Left: For when there are Openings to the Underſtanding, and Prophecies, and through the Working of the Eternal Power Joy ſprings in the Heart, then will the Enemy work ſecretly and cunningly to draw the Mind out of the Valley of Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and if he prevaileth here to draw out of this Habitation of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fety, then he will transform to lead the Mind out, eitchr (through the Motions of his transforming Spirit and Power) into Extreams, thereby endeavouring to deſtroy the true Birth which is bringing forth, and ſo bewilder the Mind, and hurry it forth (through i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginary Motions) to Diſhonour the Name of the Living Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal God, and to deſtroy his work, which through Sorrow and Travil hath been brought forth.</p>
               <p>And if he cannot prevail here, but the Light of the Lord diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covereth him, and the Power of the Lord works over his Appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance herein, then will he be at work <hi>to draw the Mind out of the Watchfulneſs, out of the daily Awe and Fear, and out of the Liberty of the Sons of God, which Libeity is (only) to ſerve the Lord;</hi> for Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion being ſelt in ſome meaſure, the Morning of Comfort &amp; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation injoyed, and Praiſes ſpring in the Heart to him that vifited and redeemed, the Enemy will be ready here alſo to draw the Mind out of the <hi>Valley of Humility,</hi> out of the <hi>ſtay'd Eſtate of Meek and Conſtant Watchfulneſs in the Light,</hi> thereby cauſing the Creature prodigally to ſpend the Portion, and to laviſh out the Injoyment by <hi>running and climing up to ſacrifice upon the Mountains,</hi> and <hi>run be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Leadings, Guidings and Movings of the Power of the Lord,</hi> into the ſpeaking forth of the Injoyment (the <hi>Prophecyings and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penings</hi> (not being led thereunto by that Eternal Power that firſt opened the Heart) and here is the Ground of the Untimely Birth, that hath been brought forth, that hath and will <hi>wicher</hi> and <hi>come to nothing.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:42915:13"/>
               <p>But now, where the Enemy is ſeen and diſcovered in all the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid Workings, and cannot prevail by theſe Snares, Trapps, Gins and Ternptations aforeſaid, he will not ceaſe, <hi>who goes about on a Roaring Lyon, ſeeking whom he may devour, and how he may again get an Entrance;</hi> ſo that he layes his <hi>Temptations</hi> according to the <hi>Spirit, Growth, Capacities</hi> and <hi>Inclinations of every one.</hi> Now after the good Work of God has been begun proſperouſly, and that the Right Arm of God's Salvation hath been wonderfully revealed, and <hi>ſignally manifeſt</hi> to bring out of <hi>Egypt</hi>'s <hi>Land of Darkneſs</hi> ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually, and that the Lord hath magnified his Arm ſpiritually, <hi>in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving many ſignal Deliverances from the Deſtroying Enemy,</hi> and has often fed with the Heavenly Food, and cauſed the Rock to yield Water for the Thirſty, and that the <hi>many Turnings aſide</hi> in the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage through the <hi>Wilderneſs</hi> have been ſeen, and the <hi>Back-ſlidings</hi> and <hi>Going out,</hi> from a Sence of the Eternal Power have been diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, &amp; that there is a coming through the <hi>River of Judgment,</hi> and the Mighty Power and Arm of the Everlaſting God drives out the <hi>Enemy</hi> that hath inhabited (where only <hi>Abraham</hi>'s <hi>Seed</hi> is to inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit) and that the <hi>War</hi> in great meaſure ceaſeth, and part of the <hi>good Land</hi> is poſſeſſed and enjoyed (<hi>even the Land that floweth with Spiritual Milk and Honey</hi>) and the Fruit of the <hi>Vine</hi> drunk of, here alſo (as in the <hi>Travils</hi> afore-mention'd) will the <hi>old, crooked, ſubtil Enemy</hi> be working, as he did with outward <hi>Iſrael,</hi> cauſing <hi>Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>run to wax fat, and then kick againſt the Ancient Power,</hi> leading the Mind out (through the Injoyment of that which in its place is good) into eaſe, and ſo <hi>to forget the Lord that made &amp; formed man, and brought him into the Land of Reſt, and lightly to eſteem of the very Rock of Salvation;</hi> and ſo leadeth into an eaſeful State, in a Profeſſion, and draws away the Mind from the inward <hi>Enjoyment of Virtue,</hi> to ſet up <hi>Idols in the Heart,</hi> and to <hi>ſerve other Gods,</hi> even <hi>Gods of Gold and Silver, and an Idol,</hi> a <hi>Profeſſion without Life and Poſſeſſion:</hi> And into this State and Condition did the <hi>old Enemy</hi> prevail to lead a People, <hi>who in many Ages had ſeen the Great and Mighty Works of the Lord, who ſaw from time to time the Arm of God Almighty out-ſtretched, and magnified in the Sight of their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies for them; howbeit</hi> (as aforeſaid) <hi>they departed from the Lord, and from the inward Sence of his eternal Power.</hi> Now here the Spirit that was caſt out, and wandred in dry Places, takes to it <hi>Seven
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:42915:14"/>worſe Spirits,</hi> and returns, tempts, prevails &amp; enters, and here indeed the <hi>Latter-end s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> worſe then the Beginning;</hi> for in the <hi>Beginning,</hi> although the <hi>Enemy</hi> had his Power and Rule, yet there was a <hi>Sence thereof,</hi> and the Heart and Mind was <hi>humbled, tender,</hi> and <hi>brought into the true Poverty,</hi> and there was a <hi>Mourning before the Lord for want of the Dominion;</hi> and this State of <hi>Humiliation, Brokenneſs of Heart,</hi> and <hi>Tenderneſs of Spirit,</hi> in which the Lord took and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth Delight, and therefore in his <hi>endleſs, boundleſs Loving-kindneſs</hi> viſited &amp; caus'd his <hi>red <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ming ſaving Power &amp; Arm</hi> to be reveal'd: But now in this other Eſtate, the Mind is high, the Heart fat &amp; full, and at eaſe, and gotten forth into the Love of the World, and the things there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, through which there is <hi>an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>amindfulneſs of the Lord,</hi> who in the <hi>beginning</hi> was every day ſought after, and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently waited for, and here the Rock (the Power) is lightly eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of; for the <hi>Eſcimation</hi> is of another thing: and here two great Evils are committed even at once, viz. <hi>The Fountain of the former li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Mercies forſaken, &amp; a hewing out broken Ciſterns</hi> (a Profeſſion) <hi>that will hold no Water, no durable Refreſhment, no durable Joy, no durable Peage nor Conſolation:</hi> And the <hi>Enemy</hi> hath thus prevailed through many Ages, to bring <hi>Thouſands</hi> from their Enjoyment of God in the <hi>pure, tender, broken, contrite, upright-ſpirited Eſtate,</hi> which he hath &amp; doth effect through his Workings and Subtilty, and that gradually; his firſt <hi>Foot-ſtep</hi> hereunto is, to bring out of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, daily, ſure Watchfulneſs, and cauſing a little Liberty to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to the <hi>carnal Mind</hi> and to the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and that gradually, and (as it were unperceivably) cauſing ſuch to take down (as it were) a Taſte, a certain Enjoyment of <hi>Sweetneſs</hi> therein, and thereby a little darkning the Sight, &amp; alluring a little into a little more Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: ſometimes his <hi>Beginnings</hi> are to draw out of the Obedience in thoſe things that were required in the Day of Small things; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times into <hi>many Words</hi> out of <hi>Watchfulneſs,</hi> no more to be as a <hi>Door-keeper in the Houſe of the Lord;</hi> and ſo the <hi>Enemy</hi> works to cauſe ſuch-like things to ſeem ſmall and indifferent things, thereby to cauſe the <hi>Offence of the Croſs</hi> in thoſe things <hi>to ceaſe;</hi> and then the Heart and Mind runs forth to make Proviſion for the Fleſh to fulfil the Luſt thereof, either in <hi>Meats, Drinks, Apparel,</hi> or ſuch like, which the Truth in times paſt hath diſcover'd and made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, and the Power of God (the <hi>Croſs of Chriſt</hi>) hath croſt, and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:42915:14"/>in meaſure lead out of, into VVatchfulneſs, in pure Fear and holy Awe, not making Proviſion for the Fleſh in any reſpect to fulfil the Lufts thereof; but drawing the Creature in Practice, as well as in Principle, into Plainneſs, and out of all Superfluities, admitting of the Creature to refreſh Nature, and not feed the Luſts.</p>
               <p>But yet the Enemy works by degrees, ſubtilly and covertly to lead out of the <hi>Liberty of the Croſs of Chriſt Jeſus</hi> (the <hi>Power of God unto Salvation</hi>) into the Liberty of the Fleſh again, and hereby gets a little farther Entrance; and though the Enemy be work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>draw forth the mind into a wrong Liberty</hi> (as into <hi>many Words in Dealings, in Commerce</hi> or <hi>Converſe,</hi> and into the <hi>Love of the World,</hi> and <hi>the Things thereof</hi> again, &amp;c.) yet the <hi>Profeſſion</hi> may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main, and the <hi>Enemy</hi> may be contented therewith, yea, and many times the <hi>Power of God</hi> may be felt in ſome meaſure, which indeed works not in the Approvement, but to draw out of the Snare; but the <hi>God of the World</hi> having by this time much blinded the Eye, and darkened the Heart, and deceiv'd the Underſtanding, there is not a Sence nor Knowledge of the Mind of the <hi>Power of the Lord</hi> in its Workings, nor a real Sence of the <hi>Decay &amp; gradual ſubtil Workings of the Enemy;</hi> for the outward <hi>Profeſſion &amp; Conformity</hi> may be in a great meaſure kept to, which is a Cover under which the Enemy may work undiſcovered by the Unwatchful: And ſo the Enemy many times leads cunningly ſtep by ſtep, until he hath lead out of the Power of Godlineſs, and ſlain the tender Birth, which in the firſt dayes of <hi>tender Viſitations</hi> was begotten; and ſo here now there will be a growing high, fat and thick; and ſuch will call the Operation of God's dividing Power Extreams &amp; Imaginations, and (<hi>Jeſurun</hi> like) will kick, and turn againſt the dividing Power of the mighty God; for all ſuch are beſt contented with a Likeneſs &amp; Image; for it loves the ſmooth things in the Wiſdom of the gifted Man, that has loſt his Way, through erring from the Power, <hi>not waiting continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally on all Occaſions to be guided thereby:</hi> So here is the <hi>itching Ear,</hi> and <hi>heaping up Teachers to pleaſe Self,</hi> to pleaſe that, &amp; uphold that; and here <hi>Jezebel</hi> is ſuffer'd and upheld; which Error crept into the Church of <hi>Thyatira;</hi> &amp; in all Ages they that went from the broken, tender Eſtate, into the Conditions before diſcover'd, did &amp; do both ſuffer and nurture this <hi>Jezebel,</hi> who muſt be caſt on the <hi>Bed of Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> and all her Children muſt be kill'd with <hi>Death:</hi> And all the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:42915:15"/>Workings of the Enemy (under every Diſguiſe) is to ſlay that which was quickned, &amp; to bring in a <hi>Contentedneſs with an Outſide Profeſſion of the Way of Truth, Light and Life of Chriſt Jeſus</hi> (the Power of God unto Salvation) <hi>whilſt the Heart is adulterated and gone from the Lord, &amp; has imbraced other Lovers;</hi> &amp; ſo in proceſs of time, where the Enemy thus prevails, he leads again into the World, from whence the Arm of the Lord gather'd; <hi>and the Latter-end of ſuch is indeed worſe then the Beginning:</hi> For the Enemy having lead to make Shipwrack of <hi>Faith</hi> and of a <hi>good Conſcience,</hi> the ſecond Death comes over, and ſuch become twice dead, and become as Salt which has loſt its Savour, &amp; are good for nothing, but to be caſt forth, and troden under foot of men. The <hi>Preſervation</hi> out of theſe <hi>By-paths, Crooked Ways, Wiles, Snares &amp; Temptations of the Enemy,</hi> is only <hi>in the True Waiting &amp; Sincere Abiding in the Light, Gift &amp; Grace of God, in which the daily Revelations and Manifeſtations of God's Eternal Power, and Right Arm of Salvation, and Preſervation is known in the daily Acquaintance &amp; Experience thereof, which keeps all Minds truly low, and Hearts ſincerely tender, wherein ariſeth an inward Travail, Longing, Breathing and Panting after the daily and continual Injoyment of the Life, Power, &amp; bleſſed, refreſhing, heavenly Virtue, which alone renews and increaſes the Strength of the inward Man;</hi> in which God Almighty preſerve all the Travellers <hi>Zion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> to the End.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Utter End and Final Deſtruction Propheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of all Falſe Profeſſions, who have had their Riſe in the <hi>Night</hi> of <hi>Apoſtacy.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AFter the Glorious Breakings forth of the <hi>Day of God</hi> amongſt the Apoſtles, &amp;c. the Enemy wrought mightily againſt that Appearance, both in his Inſtruments (by and through which he rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed up <hi>Perſecution</hi>) and alſo in thoſe Apoſtates in whom he got an Entrance amongſt the Churches, and has ſo prevailed that great has been that <hi>horrible Night of Darkneſs and Apoſtacy,</hi> that hath been ſome hundreds of years in &amp; over the Nations of the Earth; in which
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:42915:15"/>times the old ſubtil Serpent in his many Transformings &amp; Appearan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, has mightily wrought to alienate man from his God: Oh the Ways &amp; Inventions that have been by him ſet up (through his work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in the Wiſdom which is from below, which is earthly, ſenſual and deviliſh) under Pretence of <hi>Religion, Obedience &amp; Worſhip of God!</hi> What <hi>Rending, Tearing, Devouring, Murdering and Deſtroying</hi> hath there bin for theſe many hundreds of years about <hi>Religion?</hi> Firſt the great Red <hi>Dragon of Perſecution</hi> appear'd to devour the <hi>Man-child</hi> and deſtroy the <hi>Woman,</hi> but both were preſerved; then he made War with the Remnant of her Seed, and after came in another Appearance, which <hi>John</hi> ſaw <hi>riſe as a Beaſt out of the Sea, who had ſeven Heads and ten Horns, and on his Horns Crowns, and upon his Heads the Name of Blaſphemy; and one of his Heads had a deadly Wound by the Sword, but this deadly Wound was again healed; &amp; all the World wondred after the Beaſt, ſaying,</hi> Who is like the Beaſt? <hi>and</hi> Who is able to make War with him? And all on the Earth have and do worſhip the Beaſt, whoſe Names are not written in the Book of the Life of the Lamb ſlain from the Foundation of the World: <hi>And after this a ſecond Beaſt appear'd, that came out of the Earth; and this Beaſt had two Horns like a Lamb, but ſpake as a Bragon; and</hi> John <hi>ſaw he exerciſed all the Power of the firſt Beaſt, who receiv'd his Power and Authority from the Dragon, like unto which this ſecond Beaſt ſpake; and this Beaſt that had Horns like a Lamb, cauſed the Earth &amp; them that dwelt therein to worſhip the firſt Beaſt, whoſe deadly Wound was healed; and he cauſed all both Small and Great, Rich and Poor, Free and Bond to receive a Mark in their Right Hand or in their Fore-heads.</hi> And here has been the univerſal work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the power and ſpirit of Darkneſs, that hath exalted himſelf, ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the, Temple of God as God and Ruler; but (bleſſed forever be the Name of the Almighty God) the great Red Dragon, and the Beaſt that aroſe out of the Sea, &amp; the Beaſt that aroſe out of the Earth, and Myſtery <hi>Babylon,</hi> are and ſhall be manifeſt; The Wiſdom that is pure &amp; peaceable numbers theſe Appearances: and the Judgment of the great Whore is come &amp; coming, who rides upon the firſt Beaſt for now the Angel of God's Preſence is come down from Heaven, having great Power, who lightens the Earth with his <hi>Glory;</hi> &amp; the <hi>mighty Cry</hi> is now going over the Earth, utter'd with a ſtrong Voice, ſaying, Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon <hi>the great is fallen, is fallen, &amp; become the Habitation of Devils, &amp;c.</hi> All Nations have drunk of the Wine of the Wrath of her Fornications, &amp; the Kings of the Earth have committed Fornication with her, &amp; the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:42915:16"/>Merchants of the Earth are waxed rich through the abundance of her Delicacies; and the Voice is now uttering from Heaven, <hi>Come out of her my People, that ye be not Partakers of her Sins, and that ye partake not of her Plagues;</hi> for her Sins have reached unto Heaven, and God hath remembred her Iniquities; and now is the one day dawning over the Earth, wherein her Plagues, Mourning and Famine come, and ſhe ſhall be utterly burn'd with the Fire of God's Jealouſie; <hi>for ſtrong is the Lord God who judgeth her,</hi> And now in the Name of the eternal, ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>living, bleſſed God, the Creator of all things, I propheſie of the <hi>perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Deſtruction</hi> &amp; <hi>utter Deſolation</hi> of the <hi>Religions, Inventions, Ways, Worſhips, Preſcriptions, Orders, Decrees</hi> and <hi>Imitations,</hi> that have been ſetting up this many hundreds of years, and not by the eternal living Power of the living God, nor Directions, Leadings &amp; Guidings of his quickning Spirit of Life, that led &amp; guided the Apoſtles in their Day, Age and Generation; Root and Branch, Head &amp; Tail, and the whole Fabrick of the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Building ſhall be utterly conſumed, razed down and confounded forever; and all the Worſhippers of the Beaſt and the Image ſhall drink of the VVine of the VVrath of God, which is pour'd forth with out Mixture into the Cup of his Indignation; and theſe VVorſhippers ſhall be tormented, and have no Reſt Night nor Day, who worſhip the Beaſt and his I age, and whoſoever receive the Mark of his Name, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Call in the Tender Bowels of the Love of God ſhed abroad in this Day, Age and enerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, unto all the Scattered Sheep, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>HEarken &amp; give ear all ye <hi>ſcattered Ones</hi> upon the barren Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> who having loſt the living Sence that was on many of your Spirits years ago, &amp; are now ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>king the <hi>living</hi> amongſt the <hi>dead Profeſſions,</hi> &amp; your <hi>Bread in deſolate Places;</hi> Remember the <hi>days, moneths</hi> and <hi>years</hi> paſt; call to mind the <hi>days of your Tenderneſs,</hi> when the Light of God ſo ſhined on your Tabernacle, that by it you ſaw your ſelves in Darkneſs, and in Separation from the Injoyment of your Creator; which Sence brought a <hi>Day of Mourning</hi> &amp; <hi>bitter La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation</hi> on you, which was the Cauſe of your <hi>Faſting, Praying</hi> and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:42915:16"/>
                  <hi>earneſt Seeking after the Lord,</hi> with multitude of Sighs, Groans and Tears, which cauſed you to put many Days and Times apart to meet together to pour forth your Souls in ſeeking the living God, for his Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance &amp; Breaking forth by his eternal Power, and for the Reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of his ancient Arm and Horn of Salvation: And in that Day how did many of you retire your ſelves into your <hi>Cloſets</hi> &amp; <hi>ſecret Places to mourn before the Lord?</hi> And how did your <hi>Cries, Breathings</hi> and <hi>Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings</hi> after the Lord prevent the <hi>Morning Watches:</hi> And in that Day was it not <hi>Subſtance</hi> it ſelf that you ſought after, even the <hi>Revealings of the Son of God's Love in your Souls?</hi> Let me now come near, and expoſtulate with you in the Name of the Mighty God, even with you amongſt all Profeſſions that have any <hi>Tenderneſs</hi> or <hi>Breathings</hi> after the Lord remaining in you; What was it that ſtirr'd up your Hearts many years ſince thus to ſeek after the Lord? What was it that gave you the ſence of your own inward Conditions? What was it that made Sin appear exceeding ſinful? What was it that you felt in your Minds that war'd againſt the Law of Sin &amp; Death in your Members? What was it that in ſome mea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ure open'd the Eye of your Underſtanding to ſee Idolatry and Superſtition? VVhat was it that was drawing your Hearts out of the VVorld, that even made thoſe things of light eſteem in compariſon of that which your awakned Souls ſought after? VVhat was it that inwardly upheld you in Sufferings? VVhat was it that you retired your Minds unto when the <hi>Wicked</hi> raged as the <hi>Waves of the Sea,</hi> when you were <hi>mocked for the Plainneſs of your Apparel,</hi> and for your <hi>Severity in your Families?</hi> Remember your <hi>many ſignal Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verances;</hi> How did the Lord anſwer you in the Day of your <hi>Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs?</hi> VVhat was it that exercis'd you inwardly; moving on every one of your particular Souls and Spirits for a <hi>Reformation?</hi> was it not the free Grace of God? was it not that Light which ſhined on your Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle? Did not this ſhine in your Hearts, and move on your Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits God wards, and began the inward VVork of the Lord in you? VVhy did you ſtart aſide from following on toward the Lord in the <hi>Way of his Judgments</hi> when a little Proſperity attended you? VVhy did you ſeek to get from under the <hi>Judgment</hi> before it was brought forth into <hi>Victory?</hi> Be awaken'd, and come back, you <hi>Profeſſors</hi> of all ſorts, that have thus turn'd aſide for a <hi>thing of nought,</hi> which has caus'd you to wander from one <hi>Mountain of Profeſſion</hi> to another, and from one <hi>exalted Hill of Imaginations and Conceivings</hi> to another, until you have ſpent all your <hi>Portion,</hi> and are in nature return'd to <hi>Babylon,</hi> the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:42915:17"/>
                  <hi>City of Confuſion,</hi> out of which the Lord God Almighty thus calls you, <hi>Haſten, haſten to come forth, and partake no longer with her in her Sins, leſt ye partake with her of her Plagues, which are now haſtening to come upon her, and upon all that ſhall be found within her Borders.</hi> Open now your Eyes, and behold where you miſs'd &amp; turn'd aſide, through which your fooliſh Hearts have been and are darkned; for the Enemy that goes about as a Roaring Lyon, ſeeking whom he may devour, wrought in you to turn you from this pure immortal Principle of the Divine Being (that in the dayes, moneths and years by paſt awakned you, and began to work the Work of God in you) into a <hi>Profeſſion</hi> of the <hi>Words, States</hi> &amp; <hi>Conditions</hi> whereof the Saints wrote, &amp; left on re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord behind them, who attain'd thereunto through paſſing from Death to Life, in Obedience to the Grace of God, <hi>that is given to every man to profit withal,</hi> who <hi>knew the holy War,</hi> and <hi>fought the good Fight,</hi> and ſo <hi>obtain'd the Victory;</hi> through the effectual Workings of God they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd it, and not through meer Notions upon the Words of their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren the Prophets, of which Victory (through Faith and Obedience unto and in the eternal Spirit of Holineſs) they were made Partakers; and thus was it that they came to put off the <hi>old Man</hi> (which indeed is a Work) and to put on the <hi>new Man,</hi> which is a real Change &amp; Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation out of Satan's kingdom, &amp; from under his power, into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the dear Son of the living God, and ſo to be under his Power: But the Enemy of your Souls turn'd you from this free Grace of God (which was that which ſtirred in you, and wrought in you in your <hi>day of Tenderneſs</hi>) by drawing your Minds up into an <hi>airy notional Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> of this Grace, and that by it you were ſaved, not conſidering that the immortal Souls of ſuch lie in Bondage, whoſe Faith ſtands in <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> and not in the <hi>Power of God;</hi> or whoſe Faith is no other then a Belief of what is done for them without, not coming experimentally to know the Work of God in themſelves, and the Obedience of Faith which purifies the Conſcience, and makes alive unto God: And ſuch was the ſoaring up into Imaginations of ſome called <hi>Gifted Men</hi> for the Miniſtry, that they preſumed to teach and hold forth the free Grace of God after ſuch a manner, as that the Underſtandings of many were confounded, and thereby many were defiled and corrupted by admitting a Liberty unto the fleſhly Nature, and avoiding the <hi>Croſs of Chriſt,</hi> contrary to that holy Liberty, which through the Operation of the Grace of God is known: For though it is true, that (as the Apoſtle ſaith) <hi>By Grace we are ſaved;</hi> yet whoſoever holds forth this Grace ſo
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:42915:17"/>as to creat a Belief in any, <hi>that they are thereby ſaved from Condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> whilſt they are found <hi>Tranſgreſſors againſt that Righteous Law of God</hi> (of which not one jot nor title paſſes away unfulfil'd in them that walk not after the Fleſh, but after the Spirit) ſuch, I ſay, <hi>divide not the Word of God aright, but teach for Doctrine the Conceptions of their own Brains:</hi> for, its not a bare Belief or Aſſent of the Mind to the Power of the Grace, which can give Satisfaction to the immortal Soul, or true Aſſurance of eternal Peace with God; but there muſt be alſo a <hi>Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity</hi> in the inward Man unto the Power thereof; and ſo man comes to be created in Chriſt Jeſus unto <hi>good works,</hi> to be ſanctified through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out both in Body, Soul &amp; Spirit: And indeed I have found, that inſtead of preaching up <hi>Conformity to the Power of the Grace,</hi> they have not only preached up <hi>free Grace</hi> (which indeed is an Expreſſion in it ſelf proper enough to be held forth, for that <hi>the Grace of God is freely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended unto all</hi>) but alſo therewith they have preached up <hi>a Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſinful &amp; unſanctified Perſons by Imputed Righteouſneſs,</hi> even in ſuch a manner as many have from thence concluded themſelves <hi>in a State of Salvation, while Sin hath had its reign in their mortal Bodies;</hi> which I cannot but teſtifie is as great an Error, and as contrary to the <hi>Goſpel-Miniſtration,</hi> and the <hi>End for which Chriſt was manifeſt in the Fleſh</hi> (which was, <hi>to ſave people from their Sins, ſo as to live no longer therein</hi>) as the Error of the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> was, when they were ſeeking and believing Juſtification by the Works of the Law, without the Righteouſneſs of Faith.</p>
               <p>And thus hath it been, that <hi>many have turned the Grace of God into Wantonneſs,</hi> or <hi>turned from the Grace of God into Wantonneſs;</hi> ſo that in a little time, how did many Profeſſors grow light and vain, and ran with the very <hi>Prophane</hi> into the ſame <hi>exceſs of Riot,</hi> &amp; <hi>lifted up in the Fleſh,</hi> and ſo came to be much in <hi>Shew,</hi> but little and light in the <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance?</hi> And here you Profeſſors of all ſorts, that have gone from the ſpiritual Appearance of Chriſt Jeſus within, into a <hi>Profeſſion</hi> of the <hi>Saints Conditions</hi> and <hi>Performances</hi> without the Leadings and Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of the ſame Spirit &amp; Power, loſt your Way, and went out from your <hi>Guide,</hi> which would have lead you up to the <hi>Subſtance, Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus;</hi> and thouſands of ignorant people have been lead here, through the <hi>cunning Sleights of men into an empty Profeſſion;</hi> and when the <hi>Manifeſtation</hi> of the Spirit of God (<hi>which is given unto every man to profit withal</hi>) hath ſtirred in the Heart and Soul to draw the Mind out of the Ways, Spirit and Nature of the World, then the <hi>transform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:42915:18"/>Enemy of Mankind</hi> has lain near to betray &amp; deceive, by pointing &amp; directing people to run into this <hi>Profeſſion</hi> or the other, or take up this <hi>outward Performance</hi> or the other <hi>Shadow,</hi> under the ſpecious Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of the <hi>Ordinances of God and Chriſt:</hi> And hereby the ſubtil E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy (that will admit of the peoples being in the outward Practice of outward things, whilſt that he can have his Place, Seat and Throne in the Heart of mankind) has lead thouſands aſide out of the <hi>ſtraight Way of Salvation,</hi> through his drawing them from the true inward Guide (the <hi>Grace of God that brings Saivation, that hath appeared unto all men</hi>) into the outward Obſervation; and here the Fear of thouſands towards God is taught by the Precept of men who know not the Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings and Guidings of the Spirit &amp; Power of God; and ſo have heal'd the Hurt of the Daughter of <hi>Zion</hi> deceitfully, and have daubed with the untemper'd Morter.</p>
               <p>And now all you ſcatter'd Ones upon the barren Mountains of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions, give ear, hear the Counſel and Call of the Lord: Turn, you Prodigals, who have ſpent your Portions, and loſt much of your Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity and Tenderneſs, and that ſecret Injoyment you had of the Lord inwardly (years ago) and who for a long ſeaſon have endeavour'd to fill your Bellies with Husks (and the Profeſſion of the Saints Injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments) my Heart earns on you, and for you are my Bowels turned, my Soul is often bow'd down in the Sence of your Eſtates; yea, often my Heart is pained within me, when I behold your Wanderings up and down from Mountain to Mountain, ſeeking Reſt and finding none (but what is polluted) and your Souls are lean for want of the Fatneſs of God's Houſe, and you have not the Injoyment of it; my Soul is even many times diſtreſſed for you; God that made Heaven &amp; Earth bears me record, whom my Soul cryes unto even Night and Day, to viſit you with an Out ſtretched Arm: Return, return unto that which will ſhew you all that ever you have done, and that will haſten you to the Father's Houſe, where Bread of Life is; and no longer ſpend your Money, protious Time &amp; Labour for that which is not Bread of Life, but a Profeſſion, a Talk of Bread, which cannot truly ſatisfie your Souls.</p>
               <p>And now in the Name &amp; Authority, and by the Motion of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Eternal God, Behold! I ſound the <hi>Trumpet</hi> of the Lord God Almighty in your Ears; <hi>Prepare, prepare to meet the Lord</hi> Jehovah <hi>in the Valley of Deciſion; and all you who have any Tenderneſs in your Hearts, and Breathings inwardly after the Lord, amongſt all Profeſſions
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:42915:18"/>(of what Name or Denomination ſoever) Come out, come out of</hi> Babylon, <hi>and be you ſeparated, touch not any longer the unclean, that the Lord may receive you, who ſtands ready to receive all that come in Truth and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs unto him, who now will mark all that mourn becauſe of the Sins of the people, which are great, and the meaſure thereof filling up apace; and the day &amp; time is haſtening of the pouring out of the Vials of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixt Fury and Indignation of God, who lives forever and ever: And therefore ſtee, flee for your Lives out of</hi> Sodom<hi>'s Nature, and ſtick not in the Profeſſion of things, neither the one nor the other, whilſt the Ground of thy Profeſſion did not or doth not ſpring from the immediate Work of God, and daily Operation of his eternal Power in thy Heart; but come down into pure Obedience to the pure ſtill Voice of the Spirit, and Gift of God in thy own Heart and Soul, which will (as thy inward Ear is atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive) direct thee in the narrow Way of Life eternal, in which thou ſhouldſt walk: So coming here, you come to that which moved in the Hearts of many (years ſince) God-wards, which was that which wrought many into the Tenderneſs before ſpoken of; herein walk, and be faithful, and it will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ad to the Fountain of Bleſſedneſs, from which it came, and unto the Horn of God's Anointed; and to</hi> Shiloh <hi>ſhall be the Gathering of Then<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands through the Nations, Tongues, Languages and People; and the Mountain of the Lord's Houſe ſhall be exalted (through this great Day of Tryal, Tribulation and Anguiſh) upon the top of all the Mountains.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So the Lord God Almighty (by the Arm of Strength) reach all Hearts that have any breathing, panting Deſires after him (amongſt all Profeſſions) and pull many as <hi>Brands</hi> out of the <hi>Fire.</hi> So breathes my Soul, who am a Travailer for the <hi>univerſal Viſitation</hi> and <hi>Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raence</hi> of the <hi>Seed</hi> of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and raiſed up to Propheſie of the things which come to paſs, and ſhall be fulfilled in their Time and Seaſon.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>Charles Marſhall.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
